All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ס"ה, Samech
Hey, sixty-five, and we pick up at the very top of the
עמוד. amud. And we are dealing with the משנה Mishnah about פתח
petach to how you release somebody from vows, and are you פותחין
potchin בכבוד אביו ואמו bichvod aviv ve-imo or
the reductio ad absurdum בכבוד המקום? bichvod ha-makom? Why not? Basically a
policy consideration about that either then it'll just basically people just release
themselves from their own vows, it's just too universal or because people
will lie etc. So that's the first part and then the important
debate about whether you're פותחין potchin בנולד. benolad. A new event, can
that be the basis for a היתר heter for a פתח petach
and for a retroactive חרטה charata if it was an event that
could not have been anticipated. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes
on, we're going to return to this issue of נולד nolad in
the משנה, Mishnah, but the גמרא Gemara first has a very important
side discussion about התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim connecting to the what we
brought up yesterday, which was the גמרא's Gemara understanding of the נדר
neder that משה Moshe had made to יתרו, Yitro, that he had
to be then released from, probably more like a שבועה, shevua, even
though unless משה Moshe said קונם konam כל פירות עולם kol peirot
olam עלי alai if I return to מצרים Mitzrayim or if I
leave you. Anyway, that he had to get a היתר heter for
it and the question was, was that an issue of נולד nolad
or not once כי מתו כל האנשים. ki meitu kol ha-anashim. But
now there's an idea of making a נדר neder for the sake
of another person, right? And then how does that play into the
role of התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim is now what the גמרא Gemara
turns to. So let's take a look. Top of ס"ה Samech Hey
עמוד א'. amud alef. תניא, Tanya, המודר הנאה מחבירו, hamudar hana'ah me-chaveiro,
somebody who is vowed not to get any benefit from his friend,
אין מתירים לו ein matirin lo you cannot release him from the
vow אלא בפניו, ella be-fanav, except in the presence of the person
from whom he is vowed not to get benefit from. Okay, now
it doesn't exactly explain why. Let's read the גמרא Gemara a little
bit and let's sort of think about why that might be. מנא
הני מילי, Minani mili, where do we get this from? אמר רב
נחמן Amar Rav Nachman דכתיב, de-ksiv, because the verse says ויאמר ה'
אל משה במדין לך שוב מצרים כי מתו כל האנשים המבקשים את
נפשך, va-yomer Hashem el Moshe be-Midyan lekh shuv Mitzrayim ki meitu kol
ha-anashim ha-mevakshim et nafshekha, which we said right yesterday was okay, now
they're dead, now you need to be released, now you're released from
your vow because now you're able to go back to מצרים. Mitzrayim.
ואמר לו, ve-amar lo, but now we're going to focus on the
part of במדין. be-Midyan. Okay, so what's the role of the word
במדין be-Midyan there? אמר לו, amar lo, במדין נדרת, be-Midyan nadarta, לך
והתר נדרך במדין. lekh ve-hatir nedarkha be-Midyan. You took your vow in
מדין Midyan to יתרו, Yitro, go back to מדין, Midyan, go back
to יתרו Yitro in order to be released from your vow. So
you have the basis for being released from your vow, כי מתו
כל האנשים המבקשים את נפשך, ki meitu kol ha-anashim ha-mevakshim et nafshekha,
but we can't allow that to happen unless you go back to
מדין Midyan and you talk to יתרו. Yitro. דכתיב diksiv because God
can't
מתיר matir it either?
Well, no, it doesn't say יתרו Yitro is מתיר, matiring, it says
בפניו, be-fanav, it has to be in the presence of the person
to whom you took the נדר. neder. Let's keep on reading.
דכתיב diksiv ויואל משה, va-yo'el Moshe, אין אלה אלא שבועה, ein alah
ella shevua, ויואל משה va-yo'el Moshe means he took an oath, right,
makes more sense that it's a שבועה shevua than a נדר. neder.
ויביא אותו באלה. va-yavei oto be-alah. Okay, so now so he had
to go back to יתרו. Yitro. Now for what purpose? All right,
now what do you think? Why would he have to go back
to יתרו? Yitro?
Tell him bye?
Well, no, but within the context of the גמרא. Gemara. What's the
purpose if I took a שבועה shevua to יתרו Yitro that he
was not going to leave מדין, Midyan, he wasn't going to return
to מצרים. Mitzrayim. God now released him from the שבועה. shevua. Why
do you think it's important to go back to יתרו? Yitro?
Oh because if I took a שבועה shevua to you and like
it feels like you know betraying your trust or something.
Right, so there's a sense here that if it's for you so
it's if it's for your sake and it's in order to make
a the שבועה shevua is a way to make a commitment to
you then even if technically I've been released from it vis-a-vis God,
it's sort of like when you ask תשובה teshuvah for עבירות בין
אדם לחבירו, aveirot bein adam le-chaveiro, right? So okay you sinned against
God but you sinned against your friend, you're like two people involved
here. So you're being released from your שבועה shevua from your נדר
neder vis-a-vis your obligation towards you know towards God and the הלכתי
halakhic status of the object and so on but what about the
fact that you did it in order to make a commitment to
a certain person? Okay, so that would be one way of understanding
probably the simplest way. But then it's not just המודר הנאה מחבירו.
hamudar hana'ah me-chaveiro. It's not just if I say I can't get
הנאה hana'ah from Michael. It would only be in a context where
if I said that that was for the sake of me committing
something to Michael. Like I said to Michael I will never get
any הנאה hana'ah from you if I you know I don't know
if I what would I do? If I go out and I
park in your driveway again you know because you told me you
don't want me to park in your driveway. So I said that
to him as a way of making a commitment to him. So
now if I'm going to go get released from my vow and
I'm planning on parking in his driveway I better let him know
you know I have to let him know, right? So that's המודר
הנאה מחבירו hamudar hana'ah me-chaveiro in a context in which it's a
way of making a commitment to a certain person. That would be
one way of reading the גמרא. Gemara. So it doesn't have to
be המודר הנאה מחבירו, hamudar hana'ah me-chaveiro, right? It could be basically
I say כל פירות העולם אסור עלי kol peirot ha-olam assur alai
if I go ahead and I park in Michael's driveway, right? So
it's not that I'm אסור assur to him, he's not that affected
by... benefit from him that's the issue, right? The issue is is
that it's for his sake that this נדר neder was made. That's
probably the simplest read of the גמרא. Gemara. Let's keep on going
and then we'll read it.
And מודר הנאה מחברו mudar hana'ah mechaveiro doesn't say this?
I understand, but if you understand that that's what it's about then
you have to read it with that context. Fine, let's keep on
reading. Okay, וגם במלך vegam bemelech this is starting to tie into
the whole תשעה באב Tisha B'av theme now as the next פסוק.
pasuk.
I was off
of coffee for like three days before תשעה באב Tisha B'av because
I didn't want to get a caffeine headache, so it's really תחיית
המתים. techiyat hameitim. וגם במלך נבוכדנצר מרד אשר השביעו באלוהים. vegam bemelech
Nevuchadnezzar marad asher hishivio belohim. So even he, צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu, rebelled against
the king נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar and נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar had made him take an
oath in the name of God, okay, and he rebelled and so
presumably that he wouldn't rebel. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara
does with this. Okay? What was the oath?
מאי מרדותיה? mai marduteih? What was the rebellion? And also what was
the oath as we'll see. אשכחיה צדקיה לנבוכדנצר. ashkecheih Tzidkiyahu leNevuchadnezzar. צדקיהו
Tzidkiyahu found נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar דהוה קאכיל ארנבא חייא. dehavah ka'achal arneva chaya.
He was eating a live rabbit or maybe a maybe a raw
rabbit. Okay? Somehow this was some I have no idea what
does the גמרא Gemara say raw?
I don't know. I have no idea where the גמרא Gemara gets
this idea from. But anyway, he was doing this thing which was
which נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar didn't want anybody to find out about it.
ארנבא חייא? arneva chaya?
What?
Yes, that's exactly what the problem was. אמר ליה אשתבע לי דלא
מגלית עלואי ולא תפיק מלתא. amar leih ishtaba li dela megalat alai
velo tapik milta.
So נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar said to צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu take an oath to me
that you will not reveal this and that people shouldn't find out
about it. The word shouldn't go out because it would be very
embarrassing that they would hear, you know, that I was doing this,
that the king was eating raw rabbits or live rabbits. אשתבע, ishtaba,
so he took an oath. לסוף הוה קא מצטער צדקיהו בגופיה. lesof
havah ka mitzta'er Tzidkiyahu begufeih. So in the end צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu was
very anguished. Now what was the anguish about? Could be he was
anguished because of the sense of being subject to נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, but
the מפרשים mefarshim say he was anguished that he somehow couldn't keep
this inside. He needed to tell people. It's not exactly clear why.
Okay, and
but you know Rashi sort of says, if you look at Rashi,
there's a מפרש mefareish he says, מצטער צדקיהו בגופיה mitzta'er Tzidkiyahu begufeih
three lines down in the narrow lines, שהיה רוצה לגלות הדבר, shehayah
rotzeh legalot hadavar, he wanted to let people know about it, to
publicize it. שיהו, לא שיהו, שיהו מבזין אותו בני אדם. sheyeiyu, lo
sheyeiyu, sheyeiyu mevazin oto benei adam.
He wanted he wanted נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar to get an evil a bad
reputation, right? He's having problems with נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar and he has this
great little, you know, juicy tidbit that he could use against him.
So he wanted to go ahead and use it against him. So
what did he do? איתשיל אשבועתיה. itshil ashvuateih.
He went and he got a היתר, heter, right, for his שבועה.
shvuah. He went to a בית דין beit din and he got
a היתר. heter. וכשמשום דאונלא uchesheshum deonla or not? Had I known
that I would have had such a hard time
with נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, so that probably was a type of אונלא onla
that you could have anticipated. So therefore they התירו hatiru his נדר,
neder, right? So ואמר, veamar, okay, so ואמר veamar he went and
he told people about this. שמע נבוכדנצר דקא מבזין ליה. shama Nevuchadnezzar
deka mevazin leih. So נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar heard that people were, you know,
denigrating him for eating live rabbits. So he realized that now צדקיהו
Tzidkiyahu let the rabbit out of the bag, I guess. שלח ואייתי
סנהדרין וצדקיהו. shalach veaiti Sanhedrin veTzidkiyahu.
So he went and he gathered the סנהדרין Sanhedrin and צדקיהו. Tzidkiyahu.
אמר להו, amar lehu, and he said to them, חזיתון מאי קעביד
צדקיהו? chazitun mai ka'avid Tzidkiyahu? Do you see what צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu did?
He broke his oath. לאו הכי אשתבע בשמא דשמיא דלא מגלינא? lav
hachi ishtaba bishma deshamaia dela maglina? Didn't he take this oath in
the name of heaven that he would not reveal it? אמרו ליה,
amru leih, so they said to נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, איתשיל אשבועתיה, itshil ashvuateih,
he got a היתר heter for his שבועה. shvuah. אמר להו, amar
lehu, מתילין אשבועתא? metilin ashvuata? What? I didn't know you could get
released from your שבועות, shvuot, right? I mean you have to imagine,
I mean, you know, if you just come forward, right, there was
Jews got into a lot of, you know, this is why רב
שמשון רפאל הירש Rav Samson Raphael Hirsch stopped doing כל נדרי Kol
Nidrei because basically it was saying sending this message that oh yeah,
you know, Jews can take oaths and vows and whatever and then
they can just, you know, be released from them, right? I mean
in the ancient world this is how you trusted somebody that they
were telling the truth, this is how you trusted somebody to do
what they had promised that they were going to do, is they
took a vow. I have no idea if in other cultures there
was ever a concept of being released from a vow. Right? But
you could imagine it did not do the best thing for our
sense of honesty and integrity if people, if non-Jews find out that
we can take oaths to them and then be released from the
oaths, right? So
so you know and that as I said continued to play out,
you know, for hundreds of years around the כל נדרי Kol Nidrei
issue. So anyway, so he says, what? You can get released from
your vow? אמרו ליה אין, amru leih in, yeah. אמר להו, amar
lehu, haven't you ever learned מסכת נדרים? Masechet Nedarim? אמר להו amar
lehu he said to them,
בפניו או אפילו שלא בפניו? befanav o afilu shelo befanav? Wait a
minute, when you take a vow to somebody, can you be released
from it in his presence, you know, do you need to be
in his presence or does it have to be or can it
be even not in his presence? So אמרו ליה, amru leih, so
אמרו ליה amru leih they said to him בפניו, befanav, it would
have to be in his presence. אמר להו ואתון מאי עבידון? amar
lehu veatun mai avidun? So and you, what is it that you
did? You know...
Why why did you not involve me in the releasing from the
vow?
Right, מאי טעמא לא אמריתון לצדקיהו, Mai Ta'ama Lo Amritun LeTzidkiyahu, why
didn't you tell צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu that he can't be released from his
vow if he if it's in the you know it's to somebody
else unless it's in the presence of the other person? So מיד
ישבו לארץ ידמו זקני בת ציון, Miyad Yashvu La'aretz Yadmu Ziknei Bat
Tziyon, so the elders of ציון Tziyon went to sat on the
ground so they you know were you know felt thought they were
in a state of mourning, they realized that they had done wrongly.
אמר רב יצחק ששמטו כרים מתחתיהם, Amar Rav Yitzchak Sheshamtu Karim Mitachteihem,
they took their pillows underneath them and they sat on the hard
ground, they sat in אבלות, Aveilos, so either because A, because of
their you know realizing that they had done wrongly just as a
סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, but B, probably also anticipating you know what type of
a series of events that this would set in motion. Yes.
We could have been in תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av.
Yeah exactly, it was too bad, was only like a דף Daf
or two off. We could have but then we would have had
to stop, we only would have covered about half a דף. Daf.
Okay anyway, so from these two stories it seems very clear that
the issue is that it's on behalf of another person. Okay now
the question then becomes, right,
what is the הלכה? Halacha? Is this like a לכתחילה Lechatchila issue?
A policy issue like you don't want somebody you know the person
will feel betrayed and they'll think that what you know you've you've
violated A if they'll see you doing it they'll feel you violated
your שבועה, Shevua, B they'll feel betrayed that you're just getting out
of it in the first place, so you know so just in
terms of like בן אדם לחבירו Ben Adam L'Chaveiro issues, you need
to bring that person into the conversation and make them be aware
of it. Okay so that's one way of understanding it. Another way
and and it's you know it's a very important policy in terms
of people should understand that you're not violating your שבועה, Shevua, this
person shouldn't feel betrayed, you're not you need to bring them into
the conversation and then maybe it wouldn't also require exactly בפניו, Befanav,
it might you might be able to inform them of it, although
maybe you want it to be בפניו Befanav because maybe you want
it to be harder and this seems to be the subtext of
these messages particularly the נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar story, right? What? You make a
שבועה Shevua and then turn around and get out of it? So
if we say the person has to be there and you're going
to be embarrassed to get out of it with the person being
there, right? So that'll create a much greater weight to the שבועה
Shevua that's about a commitment to another person, right? Because that really
this גמרא Gemara is amazing, right? Until now we've had all this
idea of היתר נדרים, Heter Nedarim, היתר שבועות, Heter Shevuot, and it's
between you and God. So we didn't care that this was there
was this like little trick that you could get out of this,
right? It's like between you and God and that's the technical rules,
same way on שבת, Shabbos, oh well you do something it's מצטער
Mista'er with a שינוי Shinui or whatever, you know that's הלכה, Halacha,
there's rules and you play by the rules of the game and
so on, so you got out of it, okay that's fine. But
all of a sudden when it's about a relationship with another person,
how are we letting you get out of your vows? Right? The
whole role that that was playing was to make that commitment to
the other person. It it brings another person into the whole world
of vows. שבועה Shevua I think we naturally assume that but נדר
Neder maybe not so much, even when I say נדר, Neder, oh
you you were mean to me I won't get הנאה Hana'ah from
you, it brings the other person in not just as the background
and the motivation but as the live reason that sort of is
what the vow is about, right? And that sense of a commitment
to another person. So then we're saying that therefore that person in
order that it be you know we put the brakes on this
היתר נדרים Heter Nedarim which is this easy like escape path, we
put the brakes on it when it's about this other person. Now
the other person has to get involved so your נדר, Neder, your
שבועה, Shevua, you know really has some binding and meaning and you
know and binding and meaning to it. The question then becomes what
happens if you go ahead and you do the היתר Heter without
the person there, like by צדקיהו. Tzidkiyahu. Okay so fine they should
have had נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar there, it was you know very consequential that
they didn't. But but in terms of הלכות שבועה ונדרים, Hilchos Shevua
U'Nedarim, did it work בדיעבד? B'diavad? So one way of understanding is
like yeah, like how could it not? Like I mean bottom line
is a שבועה Shevua or a נדר, Neder, right, is to God,
right? Halachically even if practically because it's about a commitment to another
person, what there's no mechanism to make the other person Halachically a
party to it that they can actually control whether you're released from
your vow or not. So we can do it as a policy
matter that we insist that the other person be there, but it's
not clear that בדיעבד B'diavad it would stop it from working if
the person wasn't there. So this is the issue that's discussed in
the ר"ן. Ran. If you take a look at the ר"ן, Ran,
the ר"ן Ran says the following, he says,
he
says like this, he says take a look from the top of
the דף Daf on ס"ה. Samech Hey. איכא מאן דאמר, Ika Man
De'amar, there's one that says, and תניא המודר הנאה מחבירו אין מתירין
לו אלא בפניו. Tanya Hamudar Hana'ah Mechaveiro Ein Mattirin Lo Ela Befanav.
איכא מאן דאמר Ika Man De'amar דדוקא כשנדר לצורך חבירו, DeDavka Keshenadar
Letzorech Chaveiro, כנדר שנדר משה ליתרו, Keneder Shenadar Moshe LeYisro, לישב עמו
להנאתו, Leishev Imo Lehana'ato, וכשבועתו של צדקיהו לנבוכדנצר דמייתי בסמוך דהיינו לטובתו,
Ucheshvuato Shel Tzidkiyahu LeNevuchadnezzar Demaiti Besamuch Dehainu Letovato, it's for his benefit
as a way of making commitment. The other person to some degree
is a party of the vow. כדי שלא יבזו. Kedei Shelo Yivazu.
אבל
נדר שנדר שלא לצורך חבירו Aval Neder Shenadar Shelo Letzorech Chaveiro מתירין
לו שלא בפניו. Mattirin Lo Shelo Befanav. That's how some say which
is probably פשט Pshat of the גמרא. Gemara. ומסתברא דהא מילתא תליא
במאי דפליגי, Umistavra Deha Milta Talya Bemai Depligi, you need to
add like you know that I just said that. not going to
eat dinner by you.
Yeah, exactly. You weren't nice to me, I'm not gonna get הנאה
hana'ah from you or something like that. ומסתברא דהא מילתא תליא במאי
דפליגי בירושלמי בטעמא דאין מתירין לו אלא בפניו. Umistavra deha milta talya
bemai depelegi beYerushalmi beta'ama de'ein matirin lo ela befanav. So there's a
debate in הירושלמי. haYerushalmi. איכא מאן דאמר התם דטעמא דמילתא מפני הבושה,
Ika man de'amar hatam deta'ama demilta mipnei habusha, the embarrassment, כלומר שיתבייש
מחברו שהנדר היה להנאתו ועכשיו רוצה שיתירו לו. klomar sheyitbayesh mechaveiro shehaneder
haya lahana'ato ve'achshav rotze sheyatiru lo. Okay, that you'll be embarrassed because
it was done for that person and therefore and now you're getting
out of it. So in order to again to put the brakes
on that on the too easy getting out of we need that
other person to be present before we're going to allow that to
happen. Okay. And you should be embarrassed and maybe that'll stop you
from getting out of it. ועכשיו רוצה שיתירו לו. Ve'achshav rotze sheyatiru
lo. והאי טעמא לא שייך אלא כשנדר היה להנאת חברו. Vehai ta'ama
lo shayach ela kesheneder haya lahana'at chavero. That would only be if
it was for the sake of the other person. הא לאו הכי
משמע דמתירין לו אפילו שלא בפניו. Ha lav hachi mashma dematirin lo
afilu shelo befanav.
Otherwise it wouldn't be required. מיהו איכא דאיכא דיהיב טעמא התם מפני
החשד. Mihu ika de'ika deyahiv ta'ama hatam mipnei hachshad. It's a completely
different reason that you should not be suspect for violating your vow,
having nothing to do with whether the other person was a party
to it or not. כלומר שחברו שהוא מודר ממנו לא ידע בהתרו
וכשהוא נהנה ממנו יחשדנו שהוא עובר על נדרו. Klomar shechaveiro shehu mudar
mimeno lo yeida behetero ucheshehu nehene mimeno yechshadehu shehu over al nidro.
Right? I said I won't get any benefit from Michael. It was
actually an act of spite, it wasn't for Michael's benefit, we were
having a fight, okay. And then Michael goes ahead and sees me
I don't know resting in his yard, parking in his driveway, whatever
I'm doing. So Michael now is going to think it wasn't bad
enough that he was so angry at me he took this neder
whatever, now he goes ahead and he violates his נדרים. nedarim. Right?
And he won't realize that I got a התר heter for my
נדר. neder. So it's not because it was for Michael's sake, it
was because since it's about getting הנאה hana'ah from him, he'll see
me when I actually do what used to be forbidden and he'll
think I'm violating. Okay, so one is, so the first way it
has nothing to do with really what the נדר neder was. It
could be a שבועה, shvua, it could be a נדר, neder, it
could be a נדר neder that I'm not going to eat my
own objects, my own apples or whatever. It's not that he'll see
me and suspect me of violating, it's that it was done as
a way of making a commitment to him and he has to
be a party to the התר. heter. The other is, it's not
because of a commitment to him, it's not for his sake, but
that it's about his objects, he'll see me doing it and he'll
think that I'm violating my נדר. neder.
And usually this is conditional, we said like I won't eat your
fruit if this and that.
Right. So then the condition exactly. So let's see some of the
נפקא מינה'ס, nafkaminehs, okay. Okay. ולהאי
טעמא אפילו נדר ההוא שלא להנאת חברו אין מתירין לו אלא בפניו
דאיכא חשדא. Ulehai ta'ama afilu neder hahu shelo lahana'at chavero ein matirin
lo ela befanav de'ika chashda. Okay, so that's one נפקא מינה. nafkaminah.
Was it for Michael's sake? I would say another נפקא מינה nafkaminah
is does is it related to Michael's objects or not, right?
ותו איכא בין הני תרי לישני. Uveto ika bein hanei terei lishnei.
Another difference between these two approaches. דלמאן דאמר מפני החשד כל שידוע
לו מתירין לו אפילו שלא בפניו. Delman de'amar mipnei hachshad kol sheyadua
lo matirin lo afilu shelo befanav. If it's that Michael will suspect
me for violating, I can just tell Michael, בית דין Beis Din
can send Michael a message. Be aware that Rabbi Linzer got out
of his vow and he's now permitted to get הנאה hana'ah from
your objects. So he won't suspect me anymore, he got a message
from בית דין. Beis Din. Okay. דסליק ליה חשדא. Desalik lei chashda.
למאן דאמר מפני הבושה אפילו הודיעו דווקא בפניו דכל שלא בפניו ליכא
בושה. Leman de'amar mipnei habusha afilu hodio davka befanav dechol shelo befanav
lika busha. But if it's about embarrassment, then I'm going to need
to have Michael there and אבוחה דנצור Abucha deNatzur there or יתרו
Yisro there because that's going to put again the brakes on me
getting out of it too easy. Okay, so he gives these two
reasons, but he does not discuss here the exact the question about
the בדיעבד. bedi'eved.
Okay. Now let me just show you one more thing. Oh, so
now let's keep on reading in the ר"ן. Ran. I know we're
reading a lot of ר"ן Ran but it's just so relevant to
this. And David, I haven't forgotten about you. But let's keep on
reading the ר"ן. Ran. והיכא דהוה בפניו בעל כרחו. Vehacha dehavah befanav
ba'al korcho. So fine. I did it as a way of making
a commitment to somebody here. I משה Moshe and I did it
to יתרו. Yisro. So יתרו Yisro we get יתרו Yisro before the
בית דין, Beis Din, before God. And we're going to מתיר matir
the נדר. neder. And יתרו Yisro says, 'I refuse. I refuse to
release him from his vow.' If he's a party to it, does
he have the power to actually to release me or not release
me? I need the בית דין Beis Din to release me through
פתח petach and חרטה. charata. But if I made it for the
sake of another person, do they now become, it's again if you
think about like the תשובה teshuva model, right? Do I have to
get מחילה mechila from the person? If it's if it's not only
between me and God but between me and the person, maybe they
can refuse to release me. Or does it have to be, no,
no, no. You're going to have to be embarrassed, we're going to
put the brakes on it, insist that the person is going to
be there and if we wind up getting it he'll be well
aware that what you did to get out of it. But nevertheless,
it's
still he's not a party that can control yes or no. So
that's the question.
והא דאמרינן דלא בפניו
אלא מדעתו.
Veha de'amrinan delo
befanav ela mada'ato.
So that's the question. והיכא דהוה בפניו. Vehacha dehavah befanav. I know,
I know. So that's the question. ובעל כרחו של חברו פשיטא דמתירין
בנדר שאינו להנאתו. Uva'al korcho shel chaveiro pshita dematirin beneder she'eino lahana'ato.
If it's not for the person's sake, clearly you could do it.
של חברו ובנדר שהוא להנאתו ודאי אין מתירין לו אלא מדעתו. Shel
chaveiro ubeneder shehu lahana'ato vadai ein matirin lo ela mada'ato.
That's he's you need the person's consent. וכן כתב רבנו תם ז"ל.
Vechen katav Rabbeinu Tam zal. מיהו. Mihu. Now that again, you could
still argue that as a policy and as a לכתחילה. lechatchila.
But would it even work is that even true בדיעבד? bedi'eved? Is
he הלכתית, halachically, is he a part of that
vow according... Mechanism of the vow, not just as a policy because
of it's about you know it involves another person. מיהו *Mihu*, he
says, היכא שהתירו שלא מדעתו *heicha shehiteru shelo mi'da'ato*, let's say they
went ahead and they released him against without this person's consent. אי
שרי נדרא לא *ei shari nidra lo*, whether בדיעבד bedi'avad? *b'dieved* it
worked, צריכה עיון *tzricha iyun*, that requires more investigation. דפרק השולח משמע
דבדיעבד הותר הנדר *d'Perek Hasholeach mashma d'b'dieved hutar haneder*, דתנן התם גבי
התקין רבן גמליאל שלא יהו נודרים לישראל וכו' *d'tnan hatam gabi hitkin
Rabban Gamliel shelo yehu nodrin l'Yisrael v'chu'* etc. etc. so he says
from that גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* it sounds also, and again he says
from the story about about the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*. I'm going down to
the last narrow line. He says והכא נמי מדשרי ליה סנהדרין לצדקיהו
*v'hacha nami mid'sharei lei Sanhedrin l'Tzidkiyahu*, since they were מתיר matir *matir*
for צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*, ואי אפילו בדיעבד אינו מותר *v'ei afilu b'dieved eino
mutar*, if it doesn't work even בדיעבד *b'dieved*, היכי הוי שרי ליה
לצדקיהו לגלויי מילתא *heichi havei sharei lei l'Tzidkiyahu l'giluyei milta*, משמע דבדיעבד
שרי *mashma d'b'dieved sharei*. The story about צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu* sounds like בדיעבד
*b'dieved* it did work, right? It sounds like it was only a
לכתחילה lechatchila *l'chatchila* policy and that בדיעבד *b'dieved* it would work. Okay.
So then he goes on, he says like this.
And then four lines down in the wide line, beginning of the
lines, ומכל מקום משמע דבדיעבד מותר דאי לאו מאי אהני ליה לצדקיהו
מאי דשרו ליה *u'mikol makom mashma d'b'dieved mutar d'ilav mai ahanei lei
l'Tzidkiyahu mai d'sharu lei*. So it sounds like בדיעבד *b'dieved* it works.
ואחרים אמרו שאין אלו ראיות *v'acherim amru she'ein elu rayot*, these are
no proofs, דלעולם אפילו בדיעבד אינו מותר *d'l'olam afilu b'dieved eino mutar*,
שהכתוב צווח בצדקיהו ומענישו בדבר *she'hakatuv tzoveach b'Tzidkiyahu u'manisho badavar*, דכתיב וגם
במלך נבוכדנצר מרד אשר השביעו באלקים *d'chtiv v'gam b'melech Nevuchadnezzar marad asher
hishbio b'Elokim*. The פסוק *pasuk* sounds like he violated his שבועה Shavuah
*shvua*. So if anything the פסוק *pasuk* makes it sound that the
שבועה Shavuah *shvua* was still binding. וכן כתב הראב"ד ז"ל *v'khein katav
HaRa'avad zal*, וצא וראה מה עלה בו בסנהדרין *v'tzei u'rei mah alah
bo b'Sanhedrin*, the whole story of the חורבן *churban* of the חורבן
*churban*. Okay, והאי דקתני הבו ראיה *v'hai d'katni havu rayah* etc. etc.
Well, I don't know if that I mean but but maybe that
proves that he did that he actually part of his sin was
that he violated his שבועה Shavuah *shvua*, not just that they they
they went against the policy. So here's a question of whether בדיעבד
*b'dieved* it works or not, right, with the ר"ן Ran *Ran* ending
by saying that it sounds like בדיעבד *b'dieved* it does not work.
Okay, which again is quite fascinating because now we've taken this world
of נדר neder *neder*, which is totally between you and God, to
where other people are involved. But it always seemed to be very
circumstantial: "Oh, I'm mad at you, I'm going to take a נדר
Neder *neder*, I'm going to try to use my נדר Neder. *neder*
to persuade you." But now all of a sudden, if it's for
the sake of another person, that person has become a party in
the נדר neder *neder* and you need that person's agreement to release
you from your נדר neder, *neder*. Right, that's quite a fascinating new
idea. David, you had a question?
Is there an element of trust and faith to maintaining that in
a relationship between people? I mean here it's between two kings, but
then you
realize you can't trust them.
Right, exactly, yeah, absolutely, absolutely. Yes, Dov? Is the ר"ן *Ran* or
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* playing kind of loose with the definitions of
נדר neder *neder* versus שבועה Shavuah. *shvua*? How do you imagine that
this is a נדר neder, *neder* that you can...
Well, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, right, it wasn't, I mean the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, right, I mean it's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* starts with מודר הנאה hana'ah *mudar hana'ah* and then
takes a פסוק *pasuk* about אשר השביעו באלקים *asher hishbio b'Elokim*, and
when it speaks about משה *Moshe*, it says אין אלה אלא שבועה
Shavuah *ein alah ela shvua*, it doesn't say נדר neder *neder*, it
assumes that the same things are relevant. But you are right, I
mean since a שבועה Shavuah *shvua* is classic, the classic use of
a שבועה Shavuah. *shvua* is to, you know, make a affirm something
to somebody else, right? The תורה Torah. *Torah* knows about a שבועת
העדות *shvuat ha'eidus*, about the שבועה Shavuah *shvua* the woman makes by
the סוטה *sotah*, God makes the שבועה Shavuah. *shvua*, בי נשבעתי נאם
ה' *bi nishbati neum Hashem*, it's about making a commitment to another
person, right? So you could totally understand by שבועה Shavuah *shvua* that
the mechanism of the other person being a party to it is
much more natural to it, right? And then to sort of, you
know, say a statement by נדר neder *neder* then bring proofs from
a שבועה *shvua* is, yes, that definitely a jump.
You can sort of... does the תורה Torah. *Torah* allow you to
do התרה hatara.
*hatara* for a שבועה *shvua*? You can, yeah, yeah. I mean not
really about a שבועה *shvua* about the past because then as soon
as you make it wrong, you're lying, it's a שבועת שקר *shvuat
sheker*. But a שבועה *shvua* in the future, you know, you can
do a התרה *hatara*, yeah.
I don't know the exact לשון *lashon*, we've always said the difference
between a נדר neder *neder* and a שבועה *shvua*, one of the
differences is you're invoking שם ה' *Shem Hashem*. It almost seems like
it's the same mechanism except you're upping the ante by calling ה'
*Hashem*'s name.
Right, that's true, but it's not but I wouldn't just say it's
upping the ante because what what I was sort of saying a
minute ago in response to Dov is that the the purpose of
it fundamentally is different. A שבועה *shvua* is fundamentally geared towards making
a promise, you know, to another person. Or at least I mean
most of the cases in the תורה Torah, *Torah*, I can't think
about a שבועה *shvua* just about a person making a promise future-oriented
שבועה *shvua*. A past-oriented שבועה *shvua* is about a, you know,
sort of speaking
about attesting to the veracity
of what you said was true. And a future one is of
usually about a commitment to another person, right? So really fundamentally, yes,
it's about a שבועה *shvua* is about actions and a שבועה *shvua*
is about calling on God and נדר neder. *neder* is about objects
and God is not sort of central to that. But but if
you think about the the societal function or religious function of שבועה
*shvua* versus נדר neder *neder*, you know, נדר neder, *neder* is about
like, you know, creating, you know, making myself somehow more of a
religious life or, you know, my imagination, right? Both... שבועה is much
more
interpersonal, right? You use a שבועה in בית דין Beis Din and
you use a שבועה that you didn't lie. שבועה is
used very much in a בין אדם לחברו bein adam l'chavero context.
So what are we quoting, views like that? I'm not gonna have
הנאה hana'ah, from my friend, not this and that.
Yeah, but
that's more like I said, that's more about the circumstances and the
motivation and less about the function of it. You know what I'm
saying? Like I'm angry at you, so I'm not going to get
הנאה, or I'm trying to use this as a way to
leverage, but it's a known example, the נדר neder. for coercion or
trying to force something.
True, it's true, it's true they get used in בין אדם לחברו
bein adam l'chavero context, absolutely, which is why we could be talking
about it. But you wouldn't think of it as so much definitional
to the nature of נדר neder as much as שבועה. So to
say by שבועה the other person is a party to a שבועה
made to that person is a more natural thing to say than
by a נדר. neder That's all I'm saying. But you're right, they
wind up getting
used, נדרים Nedarim do get used בין אדם לחברו, bein adam l'chavero,
which is why we're having this conversation.
Yeah, and two things, looking at the גמרא, Gemara, it certainly doesn't
seem like you need the other person's permission. Because it says אין
מתירין לו אלא בפניו, ein matirin lo ela befanav, it doesn't say
אלא ברשותו. ela birshuto. Well he's got to do it in front
of him, it doesn't say he has to agree, so if it's
really so important that he agrees, then why wasn't that specifically in
there like that? A. And then B, wouldn't you also think that
if you really do need the other guy's mind, what's God doing
מתיר matir his נדר first versus say if you're also okay with
it, then I'll do it. Is the order a little bit reversed?
Yeah, what can I tell you? Those are all good points. But
yeah, if you want, one last thing I want to say is
if you look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot points out the mechanism
problem, because the ר"ן just says does it work בדיעבד? מחלוקת. machlokes.
So just look at one line of תוספות Tosafot and then we'll
move on. The תוספות Tosafot says the following. תנן המודר הנאה מחבירו
שנדר בפניו שלא יהנה ממנו אין מתירין לו אלא בפניו. Tnan hamudar
hana'ah mechaveiro shenadar befanav shelo yehaneh mimenu ein matirin lo ela befanav.
לכאורה משמע דבפניו היינו דבעי מדעתו. Lechora mashma dibfanav hainu dibayei mida'ato.
That the whole point of בפניו befanav
is you need the person's agreement. וקשה דהכא לא שייך, v'kasha d'hacha
lo shayach, it's not relevant. שהרי נדר מעצמו שלא יהנה מחבירו ואין
שום סברא שיצטרך דעתו להתיר נדרו. sheharei nadar me'atzmo shelo yehaneh mechaveiro
v'ein shum sevara sheyitztrach da'ato l'hatir nidro.
He basically says like, what's the logic? You did it completely on
your own initiative. And maybe what he's also talking about, and this
is the last point Jonathan about this בין אדם לחברו bein adam
l'chavero and how the mechanism is fundamentally different, I can be, there's
the הפעיל Hif'il form of the word שבועה. I can be משביע
mashbia you. I can force you, particularly in a בית דין Beis
Din context, I can impose a שבועה on you, right? Oh, you
saw, you have to come to בית דין Beis Din and be
a עד eid to what you saw. Oh no, I didn't see
anything. So nowadays we would serve you with a subpoena, right? To
come and testify. But in then we would say no, I'm משביע
mashbia you. I can force you, compel you to take a שבועה.
So the other person not only can it be done for that
person's sake and in a, to say something to the other person,
actually the other person can actually impose it. Whereas a נדר, you're
always the initiator. How does the other person have a role to
release you from your נדר or not? Okay, and therefore he says
this is all לכתחילה and so on. But the interesting thing that
תוספות Tosafot adds is the mechanism idea, particularly also the idea
that by a שבועה implicitly you can impose it on somebody else.
Does that make sense? Tell him as opposed to needing his permission,
right? What?
Yeah, you just have to tell him. Okay. So,
okay. So now let's continue. Next משנה. mishna. All right. רבי מאיר
אומר Rabbi Meir omer יש דברים שהן כנולד ואינם כנולד. yeish devarim
shehen kenolad v'einam kenolad. There are things that look like נולד nolad
but they're not נולד nolad and actually is a good basis for
a התרה. ואין חכמים מודים לו, v'ein chachamim modim lo, and the
חכמים chachamim don't agree to him. כיצד? keitzad? So this is assuming
נולד nolad doesn't work, but not everything is נולד. nolad. אמר קונם
שאני נושא פלונית שאביה רע. amar konam she'ani nosei plonit she'aviha ra.
A קונם konam that I don't know, the fruit of the world
is אסור ossur to me were I to marry this woman because
she's got a bad father, a wicked father. אמרו לו מת. amru
lo meis. Oh, then they said to him, you should know
he died. או שעשה תשובה, o she'asa teshuva, or boy he's such
a better person now. Or somebody said,
קונם לבית זה שאני נכנס שהכלב רע בתוכו konam labayit zeh she'ani
nichnas shehakelev ra betocho או שנחש בתוכו, o shenachash betocho, the
guy keeps snakes.
אמרו לו מת הכלב או שנהרג הנחש. amru lo meis hakelev o
sheneherag hanachash. הרי הן כנולד ואינן כנולד. harei hen kenolad v'einan kenolad.
It's like נולד, nolad, but it's not נולד nolad because since you've
indicated, it's as meaning,
you've shown on the one hand, the fact that the guy would
die or the guy would do תשובה, teshuva, yes we believe in
תשובה, teshuva, but I think we could say, for certain people it's
a נולד. nolad. It's not something that you could reasonably expect, a
serious change in character, right? Or that this guy who raises snakes
all of a sudden is getting rid of his snake.
Right. So it is a נולד. nolad. it's not something you could
have expected. On the other hand, since you mentioned it in your
נדר, then we can sort of read your נדר as conditional. And
that seems to be the point. That is we can read your
נדר as saying, I won't marry this woman as long as she's
got her evil father, you know, because of her evil father and
as long as that remains true, you know, so we certainly that's
how Rabbi Meir is choosing to read to read what he said.
וחכמים v'Chachamim don't agree with him, they don't read it as a
condition. Of course if we read it as a condition, you wouldn't
need a בית דין Beis Din to להתיר l'hatir it for you,
right? Because you're not getting out of it, you made it conditional.
Okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara, says.
Because the חכמים Chachamim say
it's not— you didn't say conditional. You were you you you know
you articulated what your thinking was, but at the end of the
day, you said this woman is you know is forbidden to you.
Okay? And and some new thing that you wouldn't have done had
you known that things would have changed, that's נולד nolad if it
was not something that could have been anticipated.
But wait, can't death be anticipated? People die!
No, he said before dying is a מיתה misa is not is
not something to be anticipated. An animal? I don't know.
Or you sold it?
I don't know, I don't know. Question is in what period of
time, I don't know, yeah.
But what if it actually happened and the person who made the
נדר wasn't aware of it?
Like the father died— Oh, so some want to read the משנה
Mishna that the guy had already died when he had made the
נדר. But then like then everybody should agree, that's a simple case
of טעות, taus, right? You reflected that you had certain assumptions, those
assumptions were false at the time, then everybody should agree about that,
that would have just been טעות. taus.
So let's see the גמרא. Gemara קונם שאני Konam she'ani etc. מאי
לאו? mai lav? So גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו? mai lav? Is
it not נולד? nolad? And it is a נולד. nolad. What does
Rabbi Meir mean that it's not really נולד? nolad? אמר רב הונא
נעשה כמי שהתנה נדרו בדבר. Amar Rav Huna na'aseh k'mi she'hisnah nidro
b'davar. It's like he made a condition. It's like he said, this
is you know because of and as long as that reason still
remains you know still remains a still remains present. רבי יוחנן אמר
וכבר מת. Rabbi Yochanan amar u'kvar meis. Oh, I see, I learned
this a few days ago, I forgot what I just said was
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said the guy
had already died. Of course the problem, it's the ראשונים Rishonim that
ask that's a very hard read of the משנה, Mishna, because then
why would the חכמים Chachamim disagree? If he was already dead then
it would simply I don't remember.
I don't—
it's not for the dog case. Yeah, it's for the evil father.
So you know that's a blemish on the family and you worry
about your children, you worry about your reputation, part of the family,
and with the snake, so the snake died, how does the snake
get there in the first place?
Aha, right.
That's a viper, right.
Right in the family of yeah. That's an interesting right I hear
that. Look at תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos tries to defend what the
debate would be about because then everybody should agree, it should be
a simple טעות. taus. So if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, רבי
יוחנן אמר וכבר מת, ונהוי נדר בטעות, ומותר בלא
הפרה.
Rabbi Yochanan amar u'kvar meis, v'nahavei neder b'taus, u'muttar
b'lo hafara. והכי קאמר רבי מאיר, יש אומרים שדומה לנולד, דומה כאילו
מת אחר הנדר, דיקא למיטי, v'hachi ka'amar Rabbi Meir, yesh omrim she'domeh
l'nolad, domeh k'ilu meis achar ha'neder, dika l'meisi, meaning Rabbi Meir is
saying there are things that I people might want to say make
a גזירה gezeira and say we won't allow it because it'll come
to get confused with a case of נולד. nolad. If he had
died after the נדר that wouldn't be good. But he died before
the נדר, so we're not I'm not afraid you're going to confuse
it with dying after the נדר. ואפילו הכי לא חששינן, וחכמים אוסרין,
דחיישינן דילמא מיחלף במת אחר הנדר, וכן גזרינן כשנתרפאה כיוצא בתשובה אטו
היכא דלא עשה. v'afillu hachi lo chashinan, v'Chachamim osrin, d'chaishinan dilma michlaf
b'meis achar ha'neder, v'chen gozrinan k'shenisrafeh k'yozeh b'teshuva atu heicha d'lo asah.
So according to that, the way to read the משנה Mishna is
that Rabbi Meir says it's okay because it really was a טעות,
taus, and the חכמים Chachamim say yes it was a טעות, taus,
but it but people will easily confuse it to cases when those
things happened after the נדר and then it will be a case
of נולד. nolad. Okay, so that's a way of reading it that
Rabbi Meir is really just making a גזירה. gezeira. I mean, which
excuse me, Rabbi Meir is saying there's no need to make a
גזירה gezeira here, the חכמים Chachamim say yes. All right, so you
got it. According to אביי, Abaye, the issue is was it אביי?
Abaye? No, רב הונא. Rav Huna. The issue is that he didn't
make it a תנאי, tnai, but we're going to choose to read
it like a תנאי, tnai, and Rabbi Meir is a big חידוש,
chiddush, and the חכמים Chachamim say no it wasn't a תנאי. tnai.
And according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, everybody agrees it was a
טעות, taus, but the חכמים Chachamim say it'll get confused with a
case of נולד nolad and we can't allow it. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says כבר מת וכבר עשה תשובה קאמר. kvar meis u'kvar
asah teshuva ka'amar. מיתיבי, Meiseivi, says the גמרא, Gemara I ask you
on this.
רבי אבא— מותיב רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba— mosiv Rabbi Abba, רב אבא
Rav Abba asked: קונם שאיני נושא לפלונית כעורה, Konam she'eini nosei l'plonis
ke'urah, a קונם Konam that you know food of the world are
are forbidden to me shall I marry this ugly woman, והרי היא
נאה. v'harei hi na'ah.
And you only saw her from a distance, and then when you
got up more close after you made your vow, you realized how
beautiful she was. שחורה והרי היא לבנה, shechorah v'harei hi levanah, so
or she's dark-skinned and turns out that she's fair-skinned. Interesting, because in
that time you would imagine that you know
more Jewish people were more dark Jewish people were more dark-skinned than
they are today. Anyway, קצרה והרי היא ארוכה, ketzarah v'harei hi arucha,
she was because you thought she was short and you said this
short woman and it turns out that she was tall. So now
you get to see about where people's preferences were in the time
of the גמרא, Gemara of the גמרא, Gemara, of the משנה. Mishna.
Anyway, so— so this is a later משנה, Mishnah, this משנה. Mishnah.
So the הלכה halacha is מותר בה. mutar bah. It's okay, permissible.
לא משיכורה נעשית נאה, lo mishechora naaseit naah, not because she was
ugly and became beautiful. That would be a good trick. שחורה ונעשית
לבנה קצרה ונעשית ארוכה, shechora venaaseit levana katzara venaaseit arucha, that would
be even a better trick. אלא שהנדר טעות, ela shehaneder taut, because
the whole thing was an error. Okay, you said, you know, you
said she's ugly and you were mistaken. Okay, so that was a
נדר טעות. neder taut. Everybody could agree to that. Where they actually
see something? Well, okay, that's a different story. That's our משנה. Mishnah.
Anyway, so let's take a look. בשלמא לרב הונא דאמר נעשה כתולה
נדרו בדבר, Bishlama leRav Huna deamar naasa ketoleh nidro bedavar, so according
to רב הונא, Rav Huna, that's our משנה, Mishnah, was that things
really did change in the future and that the reason that it's
okay is because we translated it as a condition. So כתולה נדרו
בדבר, ketoleh nidro bedavar, then you understand why our משנה Mishnah said
this case and the later משנה Mishnah talked about a case of
טעות. taut. They're two different cases, right? So תנא תולה נדרו בדבר
ותנא נדר טעות. tana toleh nidro bedavar vetana neder taut. Okay, because
remember this thing we just quoted about this ugly woman turned out
to be beautiful, that's a later משנה. Mishnah. So you understand there's
a debate of חכמים Chachamim and רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir when actually
the condition changes but you articulated what you were thinking but the
realities changed. That's a question of do we read it as a
condition or not as a condition? Is it נולד nolad or is
it not? And then a later משנה Mishnah says everybody would agree
that if you were in error at the time, that that's a
טעות. taut. So that obviously makes a lot of sense. אלא לרבי
יוחנן דאמר כבר מותיב וכבר מפרק, ela leRebbi Yochanan deamar kvar mative
vekvar mefareik, but according to רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan even our משנה
Mishnah is that you were in error at the time and that's
a debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and the חכמים. Chachamim. So
why are we repeating it even if you say that the later
משנה Mishnah is שיטת רבי מאיר? shitat Rebbi Meir? Why are we
repeating the exact same הלכה? halacha? So למה לי למתני תרתי זימני
נדר טעות, lama li lemitni tartei zimnei neder taut, why say it
twice? קשיא, kashya, so that's difficult. Okay. So basically a later משנה
Mishnah talks exactly about a case where you obviously were mistaken in
your assumptions and it's a טעות taut and that's presumably דברי הכל
divrei hakol and that reinforces רב הונא's Rav Huna read that our
case is a case where the conditions changed afterwards, where it was
נולד, nolad, and nevertheless even there רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir allows it
because he's going to choose to read the statement as a condition
rather than as just a frame of mind. Okay? And that's the
חידוש chiddush of רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir position here.
Just so I understand, so all these other cases we had before,
like we had טעות, taut, right,
that the משנה Mishnah says there's no problem at all, we have
to read it that there's actually מחלוקת machlokes between רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir and the חכמים?
Chachamim? No, according to what's his name, according to, yeah, that's a
good question. According to the second opinion here, רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan.
Would רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan say that every case of טעות taut
is אסור assur according to the חכמים Chachamim because it's דמי לנולד?
dami lenolad? So I assume it depends on what the case of,
on what the טעות taut is. Meaning,
and, you know, actually I spoke too quickly when I said that
according to רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan the later משנה Mishnah would be
רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. Because there are some things that cannot be,
that would not be שייך shayach to a world of נולד. nolad.
Like beautiful and ugly, white and light and dark, you know, what
was the other one, short and tall. So since there's no possibility
of a נולד nolad there, רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan presumably would be,
would say that that would be דברי הכל. divrei hakol. So that
actually would work nicely in terms of that and maybe, you know,
it's funny the גמרא Gemara didn't respond that. Maybe that was the
חידוש. chiddush. In here there's a debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
and the חכמים Chachamim because here it could get confused with a
נולד nolad case because these are conditions that could change over time.
Whereas when it couldn't get confused with a נולד nolad case, then
everybody would agree that that's okay because that anyway, but, so that
probably is what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan would say. It's funny the
גמרא Gemara. didn't even say that. But yes, that's correct, that he
presumably this גזירה gezeira that it would be confused with נולד nolad
scenarios would be limited to cases where that would be a real
concern. Okay, let's keep on reading. The next משנה. Mishnah. ועוד אמר
רבי מאיר, Veod amar Rebbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir also said:
פותחין לו מן הכתוב שבתורה, potchin lo min hakatuv shebaTorah, you do
a פתח petach for something written in the תורה. What does that
mean? So remember, there are things that we don't want to say
that are either too universal, like כבוד המקום kvod haMakom or כבוד
אביו ואמו, kvod aviv veimo, or too much they're going to get
people to say, to scare people and they won't, and they'll lie.
Meaning, you know, remember גמרא Gemara earlier, you know, had you taken
your, would you have taken your vow had you realized that anybody
who took a vow is willing to be, is deserving to like
be pierced through and to be killed? Oh, how you supposed to
get an honest answer out of asking that question? Okay, so within
that, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir said, but you actually can ask about
things relating to violations or מצוות mitzvos in the תורה. Let's see
what this means. פותחין לו מן הכתוב שבתורה. potchin lo min hakatuv
shebaTorah. ואומרים לו: Veomrim lo: אילו היית יודע שאתה עובר על לא
תקום ולא תטור. Ilu hayita yodeia sheata over al lo tikom velo
titor. And here, Jonathan, getting back to your point, right, about how
much נדרים nedarim play into בין אדם לחבירו bein adam lechaveiro realities,
even if the mechanism wasn't exactly the same.
So many of like it's so, you know, so much of what
we've seen before is, oh, you did that to me? Well, הרי
קונם, harei konam, everything of mine is אסור assur to you. You
know, it's like a classic קמצא ובר קמצא Kamtza uVar Kamtza type
of a story, right? So had you realized that not that the
vow itself was אסור, assur, but that the vow as a way
of taking revenge, right, as a way of, that that was אסור,
assur, that you were trying to... transgress, you know, לא תקום ולא
תטור, lo tikom vlo titor, ואל לא תשנא את אחיך בלבבך, v'al
lo tisna es achicha bilvavecha, or hating your fellow Jew, ואהבת לרעך
כמוך, v'ahavta l'reiacha kamocha, וחי אחיך עמך, v'chei achicha imach, or how
about that? You know, your responsibility towards him, שהוא עני, shehu ani,
and you're not able to support him now that you've made your
stuff forbidden on him, and, you know, you won't be able to
support him, this guy is a poor person. So, had you thought
about all those things,
would you have done it?
והרי זו, v'harei zo, so and, where am I? אמר אילו הייתי
יודע שהוא כן, amar ilu hayiti yodea shehu kein, had I known
that that was the situation, that he was a poor person, or
had I thought through the fact that I was violating these prohibitions,
לא הייתי נודר, lo hayiti noder, I would not take a vow,
הרי זה מותר, harei ze mutar, that's permissible.
Okay, but then רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right?
No, it's not clear that the חכמים Chachamim disagree, it's true it
says it in the name of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it's not
clear that the חכמים Chachamim disagree. The question about all these is,
look, reality is is that that's a really good point to make,
people do things in a fit of spite, in the middle of
a sense of anger, and
it's really true, had I really been, you know, been in control
of myself, calmed down, thought about that it was the wrong thing
to do, that I would be violating these prohibitions, I really wouldn't
have done it. Okay, so and we're not afraid that this is
so like, you know, terrifying, it is, you are saying you've transgressed
certain prohibitions, but we're not afraid that that's going to generate a
false response. And it is a real thing that somebody, you know,
wouldn't have,
many people wouldn't have done it had they been thinking like that.
Wait, I'm sorry, why not? Meaning, oh, you're over on something that's
מפורש meforash in the תורה, God commanded, why wouldn't that say, 'Oh
yeah, of course, I wouldn't have done it'?
You're right. So then, you know, maybe that's why we don't, it's
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir saying it, maybe there is a חכמים Chachamim
that disagree. But before we said only when it sort of came
with a sense of
how tremendously consequential it is, you're
deserving of dying, you're deserving of being
thrown in the fire and so on. You know, maybe we
don't... okay, so alright, so maybe people don't want to say that
they would have been disrespectful to their fathers, but they might have
said, you know, if I'm being totally honest, I would tell you
that even though, you know, that even though I would know that
I'm not supposed to take revenge, I nevertheless would have done it,
you know, whatever. Now, I understand, it's funny that somebody would admit
that they would have been prepared to transgress. But, you know, it
depends on how much the fear of God, how can you, if
the response to that was, 'How could you? You would have been
over on an איסור!' issur! that I probably would not be allowed
because that's not going to get an honest response.
Alright, so yes?
Doesn't this fit into the earlier category of then everybody would be
let off?
No, because not every... oh,
you mean it covers everything? Not... well, no, only vows that are
in the context of revenge and getting back at someone. But in
both those vows, those נדרים nedarim that are about a fit of
revenge, then
yeah,
I guess. But that's
a common thing with vows, right? Yeah, the only question would be
are we afraid that people will מתיר matir their own vows? It's
not as universal as כבוד המקום kvod hamakom or כבוד אביו ואמו,
kvod aviv v'imo, it's within a certain subset of vows, but the
point is, well, now we're afraid that within that subset people would
just מתיר it for themselves. I guess the point is, and this
gets back to the point that we're not afraid that people will
lie, that sometimes people are going to make vows even though people
do things that they know are אסור, assur, right? You know, so
did I just shock you? You know, people do
things. So, I guess the point is is that if we're afraid
that people, if we think that people do
it and some people say, 'Yes, I knew it was אסור assur
but I still at that moment would have wanted to have done
it', you know, so maybe that means also that we're not afraid
that people would just... will understand that there needs to be a
process here. But it's a very... I understand, it's a good question.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר ליה רב הונא בר אבדימי לרבנן, amar leh Rav Huna bar
Avdimi l'rabanan, or some have a different גרסא girsa
here, לרבה, l'Rabba, they said to either the חכמים Chachamim or to
רבה. Rabba. נימא כל דמטי לאו עלאי נפיל, neima kol d'mati lav
alai nafil, why can't the guy say, 'It's very nice of the
משנה Mishnah וחי אחיך עמך, v'chei achicha imach, and it's nice that
I have money and that he is poor, but I don't have
a responsibility to support every single poor person in the world, right?
So, you know, let him go to somebody else, I'll give money
to other poor, let this guy go to somebody else.' Now, the
גמרא Gemara is assuming that it's the גבאים gabaim that are collecting
money. But he's still say... well, we'll see in a minute, but
he's still saying it's not my responsibility, this particular person. So מאי
דמטי לי לפרנסו בהדי כולי עלמא מיפרנס ליה. mai d'mati li l'farneso
bahadei kulei alma mifarnas leh.
What is my responsibility to support him? With everybody else, I'll support
him. Now, what do you mean with everybody else? Why could you
contribute to him at
all if your נדר makes your stuff are forbidden to him? So,
what the ראשונים Rishonim say is, and it's going to be clear
from the גמרא, Gemara's is that the גבאים gabaim were collecting. So
I'll pay to the גבאים gabaim what everybody what my צדקה tzedakah
obligations are, and let the גבאים gabaim decide how to distribute it.
And so I'm not going to be shirking my responsibility, I don't
have a direct responsibility to this person. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ליה אני אומר כל הנופל אינו נופל לידי גבאי תחילה, amar
leh ani omer kol hanofel eino nofel lidei gabai techilah, that anybody
that sort of is, you know,
falls into a state of
poverty. People that become poor, you know, maybe if you've already been
poor for a while, so you're just, you know, you're already in
the system and you know you're going to get money from the
גבאים. gabbayim. But when you first become poor, you don't go run
turn to the גבאים. gabbayim. You turn to your friends, you turn
to your family.
Okay, והשתא דאמרת vehashta de'amrat and this guy presumably you have a
relationship with him, 'cause you won't take vows against people unless you
have some relationship with him. So he probably will come to you
or would have come to you or whatever before, you know, he
would have become a general collection of the גבאי צדקה. gabbay tzedakah.
And at that moment, if you weren't able to help him, you
would be over on וחי אחיך עמך. vechai achicha imach. Okay, let's
take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah. פותחין לאדם בכתובת אשתו.
potchin leadam biksuvat ishto.
We open up the person the idea about the wife's כתובה, ketubah,
about the fact that now that you've taken this vow and the
vow is forcing you to divorce her, you know, maybe the vow
was that you would divorce her, or maybe, you know, קונם konam
all of life if I don't divorce my wife, or maybe the
vow was you got angry at your wife and you said, you
know, you can't get any benefit from me or I can't get
any benefit from me, and one and you know you can't live
a marriage that way and that ultimately leads to a divorce. So
then you say to the guy, had you thought through how much
you'd have to pay out for the כתובה? ketubah? Okay, so ומעשה
באחד שנדר מאשתו הנאה. uma'aseh be'echad shenadar meishto hana'ah.
He said that his wife can't get any benefit from him. והיתה
כתובתה ת' דינרים, vehayta kesuvatah taf dinarim, and they were four top,
excuse me, four hundred, thank you point, four hundred דינרים. dinarim. Okay,
not by the way, זוז zuz is less than well, it depends
whether it's a דינר זהב dinar zahav or a דינר כסף, dinar
kesaf, but I think it's at least what? It's a lot of
money, it's a lot of money. ובא לפני רבי עקיבא, uva lifnei
rabbi akiva, he was came to before רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. וחייבו
ליתן לה כתובתה, vechiyavo liten lah kesuvatah, you have to pay the
כתובה ketubah of course that's the הלכה. halacha. אמר לו רבי, amar
lo rabbi, so he said to רבי, Rabbi, ח' מאות דינרים הניח
אבא. ches me'ot dinarim hiniach abba.
I only inherited from my father eight hundred דינרים. dinarim. נטל אחי
ד' מאות, natal achi dalet me'ot,
my brother took four, I wasn't the only one who inherited it,
my brother took half of it, four hundred. ואני ד' מאות, ve'ani
dalet me'ot, and I took the other four hundred. לא דיה שתטול
היא מאתיים ואני מאתיים? lo dayah shetitol hi matayim ve'ani matayim? Look,
let's at least just split my
money the money I've got, you know? Okay, so אמר לו רבי
עקיבא, amar lo rabbi akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said to him,
אפילו אתה מוכר שער ראשך, afilu attah mocher sear roshecha,
even if you had to sell the hair of your head in
order to pay off your כתובה, ketubah, אתה נותן לה כתובתה. attah
noten lah kesuvatah. You would, now I don't care how poor it's
going to make you, you know, you would have to pay you
have to pay her complete כתובה. ketubah. אמר לו, amar lo, he
said, אילו הייתי יודע שהוא כן, ilu hayiti yode'a shehu ken, had
I realized that I would become impoverished by having to pay off
the כתובה, ketubah, לא הייתי נודר, lo hayiti noder, I never would
have taken this vow. והתירה רבי עקיבא, vehitirah rabbi akiva, so רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said fine, okay, you're free from your vow. So
good. So he actually got a sincere answer here because it was
not even in the context of התרת נדרים, hatarat nedarim,
he's just telling the guy he's hit hard, I think it's cheaper.
There you go. Okay,
so let's just see the גמרא.
Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says, מטלטלין מי משתעבדי לכתובה?
metaltelin mi mishta'abdei lekesuvah?
Since when do you have our chattel encumbered for the כתובה? ketubah?
'Cause here רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said you'd have to sell the
hair off your head, which means like, you know, your non-real estate,
you have to sell everything, right? But isn't a כתובה ketubah only
on קרקע? karka? Now the funny thing about this is, when we
say chattel is not encumbered, that means when it's in somebody else's
hand. If I owe Charlie here a thousand dollars, right, only my
real estate has a lien, but that means that if I sell
my real estate, he can collect it, but if I sell my
car, my Ferrari, he can't collect it 'cause that was chattel. But
if it's in my hands, right, and sometimes even if a guy
dies, the heirs, you know, can collect the creditors can only collect
from the real estate and not from the chattel that they inherited.
But that's 'cause it's not the person who undertook the debt. If
it's in my hands, Charlie says you owe me that much money,
I'm collecting from any property that you've got, I don't care real
estate or not. So interestingly there is a position in the גמרא
that when it comes to כתובה, ketubah, we were so sort of
lenient that we basically said that the wife, even if the husband
is alive and it was a case of divorce, the wife can
only collect from the real estate not from the chattel, even of
the husband himself. Now if you know the נוסח nusach of the
כתובה ketubah we don't say that, right? What do we say? ואפילו
מגלימא דעל כתפאי, ve'afilu miglima de'al kasfai, right,
even from the cloak off of my back. Could have said the
hair off of my head. Okay, but at least here the גמרא
is saying, so do we see this? מטלטלין מי משתעבדי לכתובה? metaltelin
mi mishta'abdei lekesuvah? The גמרא's assuming that that the chattel is not
encumbered even in the hands of the husband. So אמר אביי, amar
abaye, קרקע שוה ת' דינר. karka shoveh taf dinar. So when it
says that he was left eight hundred דינר dinar and he had
four hundred of it 'cause he split it with his brother, it
doesn't literally mean eight hundred דינר, dinar, it means land valued at
eight hundred דינר. dinar. So the גמרא says, והקתני שער ראשו? veha
kataney sear rosho? but it says you'd have to sell the hair
of your head? ושער ראשו מטלטלין, ve-sa'ar rosho metaltelin, and
that's chattel, okay? So the גמרא says, funny because עבדים הוקשו לקרקעות,
avadim hukshu le-karkaot, anyway, הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. אפילו אתה מוכר שער
ראשך ואוכל, afillu atah mocher sa'ar roshcha ve-ochel,
even if you would have to sell the hair off your head
to put food on the table because you had been so impoverished
by giving her all of your property, all of your real estate,
I don't care. Okay? So but he's not saying necessarily that you'd
have to the hair your head would have to go to pay
her debt. You'd have to sell the hair of your head to
put food on the table.
We don't see anywhere else that the hair on your head is
specifically an asset.
I understand. You could though by for a woman's hair you can
women do that, right? They get a lot of money by selling
it. Right.
I don't think we have a case where
you
have to cut the hair off or he already cut the hair
or you have it as an asset.
Exactly. Yeah, I know. So that's why it's not—that's why we read
it as an exaggeration, right?
I remember vaguely something to do with the story of Rabbi Akiva
and his
wife
that about property she had to sell her
hair or something.
Oh, that's interesting. The Rabbi Akiva's wife sells her hair? That does
ring a bell. I'll have to check. That would be very interesting.
Okay, let's just finish.
The גמרא says like this: שמע מינה אין מסדרין לבעל חוב. shema
mina ein mesadrin le-ba'al chov. It sounds like you don't arrange for
the debtor. What does that mean? מסדרין mesadrin is a technical term
but it means that if somebody owes me money do we sort
of say he doesn't have to sell all his assets and be
left with nothing in order to pay the debt? Like we let
him to pay it off in an installment so he keeps enough
to allow himself to keep on going. That's מסדרין לבעל חוב. mesadrin
le-ba'al chov. So if Rabbi Akiva is suggesting that he would have
to sell the hair off of his head, what do you mean?
You should allow him to keep some of it to keep himself
supported until he can basically pay off the rest. So it sounds
like you're not מסדר mesader for the בעל חוב. ba'al chov. אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak לומר שאין מקורעין
שטר כתובה. lomar she-ein mekori'in shetar ketubah. No,
what it means here is not that literally that he would have
to sell the hair off the head, it means that you'd have
to pay it up in full. It's just a way of saying
that you would have to pay it off in full, we don't
necessarily literally mean that he would be left with nothing right away.
Okay, so we will end here.